
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>Tags on Topics for a lifetime</title>
   <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/tags/</link>
   <description>Recent content in Tags on Topics for a lifetime</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <language>en</language>
   <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2024 - Philipp Enzinger</copyright>
   
       <atom:link href="https://pcorvin.github.io/tags/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>Are triples into LF all errors?</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/triples/</link>
       <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/triples/</guid>
       <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started this post quite a while ago and already back then started to discuss it with a friend with some interest in baseball. The initial hypothesis I put out was: &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Triples into left field are much more common than you think&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. He directly countered that the physical path when hitting a triple into the left field is much shorter. Thus the probability of getting caught running the bases is higher than the ball landing on the other side.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that the probability of hitting a triple in the 2023 season at a plat appearance was 3.8‰ (you read that right), representing a minor footnote. On the other hand, this makes it even more special.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He was right, as statistically a strong majority (93%) of triples land in right field. The one question though presisted: How do triples into left field actually happen?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;watching-triples&#34;&gt;Watching triples&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Baseball is a data-driven sport. A plethora of metrics exist to quantify whatever circumstance in the game (even luck), where MLB is offering a &lt;a href=&#34;https://baseballsavant.mlb.com/visuals&#34;&gt;visual interface&lt;/a&gt; for better accessibility. This is sadly the only possibility to further assess how the triples came together: watching tape. Which I did for this article. You are welcome, but hold your horses: only for 2023 &amp;amp; 2024. I decided to make it as simple as possible and divide all scenarios into two.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actual Triple: The hitter had a nice hit and actually hit a triple into left or center field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Error by Fielder(s): Fielders were able to catch the ball but fumbled &amp;amp; let the triple happen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that only triples into left &amp;amp; center field were taken into account. Those were scraped of the play-by-play CSV export of all players with 5+ PA in 2023/2024. The link to the query can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://baseballsavant.mlb.com/statcast_search?hfPT=&amp;amp;hfAB=triple%7C&amp;amp;hfGT=R%7C&amp;amp;hfPR=hit%5C.%5C.into%5C.%5C.play%7C&amp;amp;hfZ=&amp;amp;hfStadium=&amp;amp;hfBBL=7%7C8%7C&amp;amp;hfNewZones=&amp;amp;hfPull=&amp;amp;hfC=&amp;amp;hfSea=2024%7C2023%7C&amp;amp;hfSit=&amp;amp;player_type=batter&amp;amp;hfOuts=&amp;amp;hfOpponent=&amp;amp;pitcher_throws=&amp;amp;batter_stands=&amp;amp;hfSA=&amp;amp;game_date_gt=&amp;amp;game_date_lt=&amp;amp;hfMo=&amp;amp;hfTeam=&amp;amp;home_road=&amp;amp;hfRO=&amp;amp;position=&amp;amp;hfInfield=&amp;amp;hfOutfield=&amp;amp;hfInn=&amp;amp;hfBBT=&amp;amp;hfFlag=&amp;amp;metric_1=&amp;amp;group_by=name&amp;amp;min_pitches=0&amp;amp;min_results=0&amp;amp;min_pas=5&amp;amp;sort_col=ba&amp;amp;player_event_sort=api_p_release_speed&amp;amp;sort_order=desc&amp;amp;chk_stats_abs=on&amp;amp;chk_stats_hits=on&amp;amp;chk_stats_ba=on#results&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-lot-of-errors&#34;&gt;A lot of errors&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is a tough verdict:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/triples_errors.png&#34;    alt=&#34;29.7% of triples into left &amp;amp;amp; left center field are fielder errors&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;29.7% of triples into left &amp;amp; left center field are fielder errors&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Part of the analysis is to redefine what an error is. Errors are defined as &amp;ldquo;in the judgment of the official scorer,[&amp;hellip;] a fielder fails to convert an out on a play that an average fielder should have made&amp;rdquo;. I thought baseball was data-driven, yet the human touch (not only umpires) persits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I therefore redefined what an error is, which is more restrive. To give you an idea, this is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://baseballsavant.mlb.com/sporty-videos?playId=7d62d974-e14d-4cd6-a2c1-45744caeed2c&#34;&gt;error&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://baseballsavant.mlb.com/sporty-videos?playId=5ec9ea5c-e2e0-4fb6-a85c-b605029a9734&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Out of the 74 triples, 22 were deemed errors with 52 clear triples. Most of the errors happen as fielders do not hold on to the ball, which is at the tip of their glove. Other notorious errors are the deflection of the ball on the floor or miscommunication between fielders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is additionally reflected in secondary stats: Nearly all (92%) balls are &amp;ldquo;hard hit&amp;rdquo; i.e. the ball is hit with 150 kph. Ball speed is often paired with launch angle, concluding in &amp;ldquo;barrels&amp;rdquo;, which have a high probability to end up as home runs. The barrel probability of all triples analyzed is 32.8%, where 15%+ barrel rate is considered elite.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the outcome of the balls in play does not directly translate into an automatic triple and not even a double. xSLG highlights the expected outcome of all balls put in play by a player. &lt;a href=&#34;https://miniwebtool.com/slugging-percentage-calculator/&#34;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; is a helpful tool to understand what slugging (SLG) means, where xSLG is the expected outcome based on the player&amp;rsquo;s exit velocity &amp;amp; launch angle. Despite the high barrel rate, the average xSLG is 1.243, which translates into an automatic single (reaching first base) but not beyond that. This is validated by comparing SLG &amp;amp; xSLG, boasting an average difference of 1.757.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;umpires-are-humans-too&#34;&gt;Umpires are humans too&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on the statistical analysis, we can understand that triples into left field are somewhat dependent on the performance of fielders, letting go of balls in play even though they should normally have it. At the end, multiple factors, which go beyond this high-level overview, such as sprint speed help to score triples even when the probabilities are lower. The comparison to force outs at third base would also highlight how many players got caught in the process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, triples into left field are still a fraction (13.4%) of all triples happening in the game, where right field is a better location to hit them (although the SLG-xSLG is still high). And they happen way more often due to errors than you think. Blame the umpires for that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>LLM benchmarks do not inform their actual performance.</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/metrics/</link>
       <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/metrics/</guid>
       <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a high-level analysis of current benchmarks for large language models (LLMs) that are developed by OpenAI, Anthropic, Mistral, et al. Note that I do not have an immediate answer on how to solve this, yet wanted to highlight a “devil’s advocate” answer to existing cries of LLMs to rule everything.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am by no means an expert in LLMs, nor foundational models (who truly is?) but I stuck with Deep Learning for quite a bit. My focus then &amp;amp; now was a bit different, building new, modular network structures with the building blocks available. The famous “Attention is all you need” paper was interesting when it came out, I used the structure for auto-encoder structures in feature abstraction. GPT-2 was also interesting, but not worth using, nor at a scale where it mattered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A couple of years later it escalated. Businesses build on top foundation models &amp;amp; raise gargantuan seed rounds, mostly without looking at the fundamentals: checking whether it makes sense to use foundational models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main drivers to choosing your LLM are benchmarks, which tell you how much better one is relative to the other. People would rely on an 85.9% MMLU, without any deeper understanding, nor insight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We thus want to dive into the most common benchmarks, why they do not always (I know, clickbait) reflect on the actual performance &amp;amp; why you might look beyond the current leader of the LLM Leaderboard.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-the-main-benchmarks&#34;&gt;What are the main benchmarks?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might have checked in on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://huggingface.co/spaces/open-llm-leaderboard-old/open_llm_leaderboard&#34;&gt;Hugging Face LLM leaderboard&lt;/a&gt;, whichrepresents the industry standard for comparison of LLMs. To have a more complete picture, a sample of SoA metrics willbe represented by this bunch with their category highlighted in &lt;em&gt;italic&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/mmlu&#34;&gt;MMLU&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; - Multitask accuracy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rowanzellers.com/hellaswag/&#34;&gt;HellaSwag&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;reasoning&lt;/em&gt; - Understanding situations&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/openai/human-eval&#34;&gt;HumanEval&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; - Python coding tasks&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/openai/grade-school-math&#34;&gt;GSM-8K&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;math/reasoning&lt;/em&gt; - Grade school math&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.03874&#34;&gt;MATH&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;math&lt;/em&gt; - Math problems with 7 difficulty levels&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that these metrics represent their respective category, although you might highlight a missing metric orthat some of these are outdated already: bear with me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-wrong-with-them&#34;&gt;What is wrong with them?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Personal bias led to this selection of these metrics and confirm the hypothesis highlighted at thebeginning. Let us dive into the respective categories:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;knowledge&#34;&gt;Knowledge&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;MMLU is not good. In fact, the community already developed a successor called &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01574&#34;&gt;MMLU-Pro&lt;/a&gt;, whichinherits parts of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MMLU stands for Massive Multitask Language Understanding and should represent a general knowledge database, which aggregatesquestions &amp;amp; answers on various topics from different sources. You see the catch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The benchmark questions contain wrong answers to questions, no answer at all or bad formulation of questions. Furthermore, the splitin topics, their share &amp;amp; what sources are taken into account are not fully documented. If you are interestedin the taxonomy and what can be done better, feel free to access the paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04127&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, Hugging Face &amp;amp; their newest iteration of the LLM leaderboard (&lt;a href=&#34;https://huggingface.co/spaces/open-llm-leaderboard/open_llm_leaderboard&#34;&gt;different link than above&lt;/a&gt;)included MMLU-Pro, which has revisited questions. Despite the efforts of human fact-checking, the question about the sources of answers and theirsystematic checking, remains: How can validate ground truth and how to highlight trusted sources for each subject?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;HumanEval suffers from a similar fate, as the coding examples and their narrative are ambiguous.Most of the examples are too simple to be reflected in complex developer environments (you might have worked with Github Co-Pilot),where larger code structures pose major problems due to the small context windows.A new adoption can be driven by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Leolty/repobench&#34;&gt;RepoBench&lt;/a&gt;, which takes working Github production repositoriesas a comparison for auto-completion systems. Performance of LLMs on these remains &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2306.03091&#34;&gt;low&lt;/a&gt;, especially because of the diversityof tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;reasoning&#34;&gt;Reasoning&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;HellaSwag reached saturation, i.e. it is too easy for LLMs to reach near human performance. This clashes with the commonperception of LLMs hallucinating and not grasping Newton&amp;rsquo;s law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, it is mainly due to already shared information datasets or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/code/alexisbcook/data-leakage&#34;&gt;data leakage&lt;/a&gt; happening in trainings. LLMs wouldgain access to the validation data during training &amp;amp; prior to the benchmarking process, thus defeating the purpose.GSM-8K is an example for it, which then do not assess the general performanceof the LLM but rather overfitting to the specific data. When tasked  to propose other metrics for reasoning benchmarking, GPT3.5 comes back to HellaSwag as alternative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next iteration of reasoning metrics is already in place: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16049&#34;&gt;MuSR (Multistep Soft Reasoning)&lt;/a&gt;is a collection of problems to solve, spanning various topics with varying length. Current performances of LLMs show thatthey are at best random in the selection of their answers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;math&#34;&gt;Math&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mathematical logic remains a big if for LLMs with several recurring posts about basic operators not being correctly used&amp;amp; interpreted. MATH remains a solid benchmark &amp;amp; reflects the complexity of math problems in high school. Models do not performwell in this metric specifically,  as the combination of mathematical statements &amp;amp; plain text becomes more complex to understand.Current models (Status 07.2024) stick within the low 50s, compared to 80-90s in pure language-based tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In case you are interested in strong mathematical performance, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/ai-solves-imo-problems-at-silver-medal-level/&#34;&gt;non-LLM deep learning networks&lt;/a&gt;which faired much better under pressure on a higher level.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes--general-benchmarking-sanity&#34;&gt;Changes &amp;amp; general benchmarking sanity&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;A benchmark is only as good as its data. And metrics might wear out. Metrics get renewed once a plateau of currentperformance can be observed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Practical &amp;amp; realistic benchmarks such as RepoBench or the Math Olympiad would be great comparisons, yet might fail to validatethe performance due to the higher complexity. The current times demand a flexible framework given the fast pace at whichmodels are iterated over and achieve new limits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, consumers &amp;amp; users should think about their testing suite and what matters most to them. If knowledge basesis what you are looking for, kindly ignore math &amp;amp; reasoning to fully focus on how good a LLM can retrieve &amp;amp; understand datathrough your own RAG infrastructure. If you want to build an AI assistant for children in primary school, math problems might be a majorfactor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lastly, do not blindly trust labs publishing the newest results and stressing that their model is the best. Do yourown research and decide what matters most to you and how you can benefit most from what is currently available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As usual, it depends on your use case.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in the evolution of LLM comparison, have a look at the Hugging Face blog of the LLM leaderboard.They do their best to keep the comparison as neutral &amp;amp; up to date as possible with explanations of the changes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Defense Industry &amp; Strategy in Austria as example of major NATO procurement</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/austria/</link>
       <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/austria/</guid>
       <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is an exemplary overview of a local defence industry and shedding some light on what is currently within the arsenal of NATO armies.If you have any other example or comments, feel free to reach out!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am from Austria is not only the unofficial hymn of the central European country but also what I tell people asking me where I am from.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apart from Schnitzel &amp;amp; skiing, a first touchpoint is the compulsory military service still in place, which somewhat makes sense for neutral countries (Hi Switzerland!).As I had to fulfill it in 2014, little did I know about how the cogs &amp;amp; wheels are turning regarding the procurement of military equipment.Back then, the tools at disposal were by no means modern and limited investment meant a bleak peak into the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This seems to be no different to other defense apparatus in Europe, where legacy platforms are maintained and only ever since the recentconflicts in Ukraine &amp;amp; Israel, have modern stacks been applied &amp;amp; tested. Modernizing these systems (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://helsing.ai&#34;&gt;Helsing&lt;/a&gt;) orstarting completely new platforms (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://anduril.com&#34;&gt;Anduril&lt;/a&gt;) are only starting to win specific contracts against existing primes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-taking-austria-to-compare-it-to-nato&#34;&gt;Why taking Austria to compare it to NATO?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Austria is not part of NATO (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Austrian_State_Treaty&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more explanation) but nevertheless represents a great case study on how &amp;ldquo;Western&amp;rdquo; countriestry to modernize their fleet but still spend the majority on flagship &amp;amp; existing platforms, diving into somewhat newer paradigms of the 2000sand only slightly touching new platforms to shift to a more dynamic arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main point focuses on the different systems &amp;amp; tools leveraged in the past years, with some outlook on how they can be merged in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-old-guard-traditional-arms-procurement&#34;&gt;The old guard: traditional arms procurement&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking at the most prized assets in the defense sector, two names will be directly flagged: &lt;a href=&#34;https://eu.glock.com/en&#34;&gt;Glock&lt;/a&gt;&amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.steyr-arms.com/en/&#34;&gt;Steyr&lt;/a&gt;, both local firearms producers.The former notorious pistol was everaged by regular police forces as well as special forces of the US, Germany &amp;amp; France. The latter exports itsAUG, an assault rifle, is used across the world, although also in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/world/syria-rebels-bolstered-by-new-arms-but-divisions-remain-idUSBRE91P0PV/&#34;&gt;parts you might not want to see it&lt;/a&gt;.Apart from firearms, Steyr-Daimler-Puch, unrelated to the firearms department and within General Dynamics, focuses on their Pandur vehicle.This armoured personnel carrier (APC) is built for internal usage but was recently exported to Belgium, Slovenia, Ukraine &amp;amp; the US.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These exports represented around 75% of the procured defense products out of Austria in 2021. Nearly all buyers are NATO countries, apart fromspecific NATO allies (Saudi Arabia, Philippines, Thailand) and other countries such as Kuwait&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, this reflects the current majoritarian spending of the procurement budget within NATO. Legacy systems are still fuelled, althoughshifts happened over time given the allocation of research budget in the past &amp;amp; seeing automated/semi-autonomous systems being integratedwithin the field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-shift-uavs--reconnaissance&#34;&gt;The shift: UAVs &amp;amp; reconnaissance&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://schiebel.net&#34;&gt;Schiebel&lt;/a&gt; might not be known to everybody, given their niche product, but is one of the strongest defense companies in Austria.Their main selling point revolves around Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs), which instantiate on a selected mission (althoughthey additionally cover a mine detection program). This can be any flight to take pictures of a specified target at alocation or monitoring infrastructure in remote areas. In the defense context, understanding what happens at places you cannot directly reach(think enemy territory on the other of a mountain) and need high granularity (satellites will not work) is invaluable and can be covered byUAVs. Additional payloads beyond high-resolution cameras can be mounted to provide insights in dark environments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Missile types cannot be flown by the Camcopter (the name of Schiebel&amp;rsquo;s product) and only a selected number of militaries have them at this stage.Specifically autonomous drones, which are marketed as a new primitive, remain sparse, with mostly the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Atomics_MQ-9_Reaper&#34;&gt;Predator/Reaper&lt;/a&gt;and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TAI_Aksungur&#34;&gt;TAI/Bayraktar family&lt;/a&gt; being the only major products being produced at this stage by NATO members.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might have heard of other NATO countries having drones on their own or developing these on their own (UK, France, EU), yet they remaindependent on their counterparts to allow procurement of the existing UAV infrastructure, which remains fairly limited&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-newcomers-osint--data-infrastructure&#34;&gt;The newcomers: OSINT &amp;amp; data infrastructure&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blackshark.ai&#34;&gt;Blackshark.ai&lt;/a&gt; rose to fame through Microsoft Flight Simulator. Seems odd, but the pixel mesh in its newest iteration was notas mushy as in its predecessors thanks to Blackshark. Their work focuses on satellite data to be augmented by machine learning to include &amp;amp;extract more detailed information in real time. Their &lt;a href=&#34;https://blackshark.ai/bisim-and-blackshark-ai-join-forces/&#34;&gt;deal&lt;/a&gt; withBISim is the start of their defense branch and more specifically to target capabilities beyond the currentcapabilities with their annotation &amp;amp; finding tool &lt;a href=&#34;https://blackshark.ai/orcahuntr/&#34;&gt;Orca Huntr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The use case for national defense is in Open Source Intelligence (short OSINT), especially regularly extracting as much information for surveillanceand pot. targets. OSINT has very much grown in recent years, with more intelligence agencies investing largershares of their budgets. UAVs &amp;amp; their reconnaissance would be partly complementary, although the former focuses more on strikesrather than information gathering. Knowing as much in advance as possible is necessary to not waste any additional resourceswithin a mission, namely your UAV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These software solutions represent a new way of combative strategy and level up the possibilities to develop &amp;amp; validate plans forconcrete missions to determine how to leverage the existing arsenal. A key player is Anduril with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anduril.com/command-and-control/&#34;&gt;Lattice&lt;/a&gt;enabling C2 (command &amp;amp; control) capabilities for orchestration &amp;amp; coordination of actions. The NATO &amp;amp; existing large industry titans startedtheir &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.act.nato.int/article/nato-centres-of-excellence-command-and-control-c2-coe/&#34;&gt;initiative&lt;/a&gt; on their own, yet remains to beseen how novel architecture and tooling will be implemented within the upcoming years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;piecing-the-new-procurement-strategy-together&#34;&gt;Piecing the new procurement strategy together&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on the three parts, you can observe the switch from one step of the OODA to another. OODA stands for Observe, Orient, Decide &amp;amp; Act, a militarymantra to reach a decision. Whilst focusing on the Act part for most of the time, with soldiers being responsible for the rest, previous iterationsin procurement cycles were mostly spent on Act (again) and Observe. Only recently were Orient &amp;amp; Decide taken into account with the rise of MLsolutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, NATO &amp;amp; its members try to focus more of their budget research initiatives, clustering around autonomous systems (covering OODA whilst keeping the human within Decide)and new information-gathering systems within their next generation of infrastructure (mainly on Observe &amp;amp; Orient). The major share of capitalremains allocated to legacy systems, with only limited thought in published strategies on how to connect existing tools within the newset of requirements and the future of military systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is directly reflected within the defense industry in Austria: Major existing players staying on top, limited innovation to integrateinto new systems revolving around different aspects of the battlefield than theirs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/DE/TXT/PDF/?uri=CELEX:52023XG0216(01)&amp;amp;qid=1681985654900&amp;amp;from=De&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://armstransfers.sipri.org/ArmsTransfer/TransferData/transferResults?logic=on&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unmanned_combat_aerial_vehicle#Current&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Poor Tommy John: Ruining baseball&#39;s future</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/tommyjohn/</link>
       <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/tommyjohn/</guid>
       <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gQujXQQGOVNaiuwSN680Hq-FDVsCwvN-3AazykOBON0/edit#gid=0&#34;&gt;Tommy John Surgery Data&lt;/a&gt;, which provided all data used in this article!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Tommy John injured himself in 1974, he was out indefinitely. Nobody knew what was happening &amp;amp; no doctor was able to fix it. Tommy John (TJ) was not a high performer but a stellar contributor across his 26 years in the league. The &amp;ldquo;Bionic Man&amp;rdquo; started a revolution in the sport of baseball, which heavily impacts it today: he heavily bruised his elbow &amp;amp; got it fixed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When mentioning Tommy John Surgery today, friends of the national pastime show a disgusted face &amp;amp; grumble something like &amp;ldquo;looking forward to see him next year!&amp;rdquo;. What requires the procedure in the first place is the rupture of the ligament in your elbow (similar to the knee), which is then replaced by something from somewhere else of your body. As you might not from any MCL/ACL injuries, it takes time to train them &amp;amp; it is the same for your elbow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem though? Football pitchers &amp;amp; skiers break their legs over the years, and they are fine (they are not, different topic), right? Technically this also applies to baseball, although the rate of it happening is alarming. Tommy John would normally occur to pitchers only (the people throwing 160+ kph balls at you), as they overflex their elbows to execute their pitches (throws) with a maximum of velocity &amp;amp; break. Yet, currently, the system breaks with the highest share of athletes needing Tommy John being 15 to 19 years old (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/765898&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Especially at this young age, having underdeveloped muscles &amp;amp; core, the pipeline for pitchers dries up faster than initially planned. This furthers thins out the number of pitchers available throughout the minors &amp;amp; major league, which is becoming increasingly difficult. Pitch count is the main metric coaches consider when replacing starting pitchers &amp;amp; bullpen arms. Looking at the age of pitchers getting TJ surgery, a worrying trend can be seen:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/age.png&#34;    alt=&#34;Pitchers are getting TJ surgery younger than ever over the past 20 years&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;Pitchers are getting TJ surgery younger than ever over the past 20 years&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a recent uptick, the trend towards early TJ surgery was in decline, where the median age in 2000 was 24.2 years and bottomed out at 21.98 in 2016 (9.17% drop). It drifted back to normal in recent years. Nevertheless, the constant rise in TJ surgeries is alarming, being close to triple of what it was 20 years ago (29 to 94). A key ingredient backing up this up is the general level when pitchers get their first TJ surgery, which goes from college as a majority up to the big leagues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/levels.png&#34;    alt=&#34;An uptick in especially college pitchers is worrying, from 2010 onwards&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;An uptick in especially college pitchers is worrying, from 2010 onwards&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When putting this further into perspective of the two key major levels with TJ surgeries, we can clearly observe that reversal happening:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/coll_pro.png&#34;    alt=&#34;College pitchers got back to normal, MLB pitchers escalating&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;College pitchers got back to normal, MLB pitchers escalating&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Especially in the early 2024 season, MLB already reached the TJ levels of the past years, with the season just starting. Most of the changes on a college level can be traced back to the athletics department setting a higher priority on preventing elbow injuries through easy pre-season programs &amp;amp; less wear in games.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When considering the minor league system, we can relate to the COVID times &amp;amp; the disproportionate number of wear &amp;amp; tear players&amp;rsquo; aftermaths, as the minor league season was drastically reduced early on:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/minors.png&#34;    alt=&#34;The COVID hiccup in 2020 with a rebound in 2021&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;The COVID hiccup in 2020 with a rebound in 2021&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minor league injuries are at lower levels, especially compared to the number of total players in the system: Considering the ±270 players in a minor league system per club &amp;amp; the 40-man roster in MLB, the likelihood of a TJ injury for one of the ± 14 pitchers is 4.62x likelier (5.083% vs. 1.098%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But what can we do?&lt;/strong&gt; Nothing. Especially offspeed pitchers are prone to TJ &amp;amp; will stay, given the extreme horizontal &amp;amp; vertical movement of pitches. Recent years were a success nevertheless, focusing more on pitch prevention (staying below 100 pitches) as well as the introduction of less intense off-speed pitches overall (hello sweeper!). Overall, it might be best to start pitching the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qusYTWQFIF8&#34;&gt;knuckleball&lt;/a&gt; again. Story for another day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
