
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>Categories on Topics for a lifetime</title>
   <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/categories/</link>
   <description>Recent content in Categories on Topics for a lifetime</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <language>en</language>
   <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2024 - Philipp Enzinger</copyright>
   
       <atom:link href="https://pcorvin.github.io/categories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>I love you, Wilyer</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/wilyer/</link>
       <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/wilyer/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Wilyer Abreu has been one of the top rookies in baseball this season. Along with playing above-average defense in right field, the 24-year-old Boston Red Sox outfielder has logged a 155 wRC+ while slashing .316/.396/.519 over 91 plate appearances. His 1.1 WAR ranks second among rookie position players, behind Baltimore’s Colton Cowser. Granted, less than a month’s worth of games is hardly enough time to know if he’ll keep this up, but Abreu’s strong start is encouraging nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He similarly impressed last year in a 28-game cameo. Debuting in late August, Abreu went 24-for-76 (.316) with two home runs, the exact same numbers he had this April. There’s juice in his bat. Eric Longenhagen wrote last summer that Abreu “has above-average raw power,” and the youngster’s production has backed up that prose. By the time of his call-up, Abreu had gone yard 22 times, with a 135 wRC+, at Triple-A Worcester.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His path to the big leagues included more than your typical climb up the minor league ladder. The Red Sox acquired Abreu from the Houston Astros, along with Enmanuel Valdez, in the trade for Christian Vázquez on August 1, 2022 — but that’s also only part of the story. The Maracaibo, Venezuela native had intended to sign with Boston in 2016, but the Red Sox were locked out of the international amateur market in 2016-17 as punishment for violating international-signing regulations. Abreu subsequently signed with the Astros in 2017; he waited an extra year to sign because he was told he’d get a better offer if he did.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He’s evolved as a hitter since inking his first professional contract.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I’ve changed a lot,” Abreu told me recently through translator Carlos Villoria-Benítez. “Maybe the swing is similar to back then, but the posture and the stance have changed throughout the years. Year to year, I was making adjustments, looking for the correct position, correct stance, that was most comfortable.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly, analytics and technology were involved in the process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That Abreu’s first full season in the Red Sox system was both statistically his best as a professional, and culminated in a big league call-up, was aided by another adjustment. It was two-fold, with the same goal in mind.“One of the things we worked on after I got here was my hand position,” Abreu said. “Also my stance, I think my stance was a little bit too open. They had me close it a little bit so that my hands are closer to the firing position.” The purpose of this adjustment was to cut down on the movement in his swing before he attacks the baseball. That brings us to what he feels is the key to his having success at the dish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I love you, Wilyer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>UZR vs. DRS: FIGHT!</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/defense/</link>
       <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/defense/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;I love defensive metrics over everything. They have something of a randomness factor to this statistical game of baseball. You might ask: Why random?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of confusion and misinformation out there, so I’d love the opportunity to set it straight. I’ll outline the metric I’m most familiar with (UZR) and then dive into the other one (DRS). This is a specific write-up to unpack the overall complexity in defensive metrics for position players, especially under the circumstance of the respective pitchers &amp;amp; the ball in play.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit:&lt;/em&gt; Thank you Bailey for covering &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yT0dWF4BTbk&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. I might nevertheless add context in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Bye Bye Chris</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/chris/</link>
       <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/chris/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Chris Sale came to the Boston Red Sox as an absolute treasure. One of the great pitchers of his era, still firmly in his prime, Sale arrived in a blockbuster 2016 trade that signaled the Red Sox’s all-out pursuit of a championship. Within two years, he recorded the final out of the World Series. Sale was dominant and dependable, with a certain swagger that fit an organization at the top of the sport.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Sale left as an albatross. Traded in the final year of a five-year, $145 million extension that hamstrung the organization throughout its fall to the bottom of the American League East, Sale had become many of the things he never wanted to be on a baseball field. Unavailable. Unreliable. Overpaid. He’d become a wild card on a team that desperately needed stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Red Sox traded Sale to the Atlanta Braves Saturday for 22-year-old infielder Vaughn Grissom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Anytime you trade someone like Sale who has made such a meaningful contribution to this organization and was obviously an incredibly important part of a World Series-winning team, it’s a really tough, tough decision,” chief baseball officer Craig Breslow said. “The fact that I wasn’t the chief baseball officer here didn’t diminish that in my mind at all. So it’s something that I was very mindful of and very thoughtful of, but in the end, I felt like this was a decision that was best for the Red Sox, both in the near term and the long term. So it was one that I needed to do.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to a person familiar with the terms of the transaction, the Red Sox will pay $17 million of Sale’s $27.5 million salary this season. With $10 million of Sale’s salary deferred, the Braves are getting him for next to nothing in the short term, but they’re giving up a good young player in the process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Red Sox are gaining long-term stability with Grissom, who various team sources said will move firmly into the mix at second base, where he’s expected to be at the top of the depth chart heading into spring training. Grissom still has six years of team control remaining and had a .921 OPS in Triple A last season. The Red Sox have had a revolving door at second base since the heyday of Dustin Pedroia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which is perhaps yet another reminder that injuries can derail even the greatest of careers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sale was one of baseball’s best starting pitchers from 2012 to 2018. He was a first-round MLB Draft pick in 2010 and got to the big leagues within months. After moving into the Chicago White Sox’s rotation in 2012, he finished top six in the American League Cy Young voting five years in a row while making five consecutive All-Star teams. The Red Sox acquired him in December 2016 for a prospect package headlined by Yoán Moncada — at the time, one of the top prospects in the sport — and Michael Kopech. Sale remained truly elite for two more years, just long enough to win the 2018 championship and sign an extension the following spring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then it all fell apart. Sale’s 2019 season was, at the time, the worst of his career, and late-season elbow inflammation proved a precursor to 2020 Tommy John surgery. He returned in late 2021 but struggled in the playoffs, then fractured a rib in the lead-up to 2022 spring training, broke his pinky in his second start off the injured list and broke his wrist in a bike accident late that season. Last year, Sale made 20 starts but also missed almost two months with a stress reaction in his scapula.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I hate feeling like this,” Sale said when he was shut down in early June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Throughout the setbacks and disappointments, Sale remained a popular teammate. His desire never waned. His body simply let him down. And when healthy, Sale was still an intimidating and motivating presence. Although his velocity dipped at times last season, his fastball still averaged between 93 and 94 mph. He still generated swing-and-miss and poor contact at rates better than 75 percent of pitchers in the league, according to Statcast. After a rocky first few outings last season, Sale had a 3.16 ERA in his last 15 starts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But he also went more than five innings only once after May 20.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a Braves team coming off a 104-win season, Sale might be a worthwhile gamble. At his best, he can still be a difference-maker, and the Red Sox believed even in years past that he would still have some trade value if he could just get into an offseason healthy. He finally did that this year. His contract includes a $20 million club option for 2025, which becomes guaranteed if he finishes top 10 in Cy Young voting and does not end 2024 on the injured list.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>The obligatory Adam Dunn article</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/adam/</link>
       <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/adam/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Adam Dunn was a thoroughly weird player.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not in the physical sense. Don’t be gross.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I mean is that Dunn, through no fault of his own, became more than a single baseball player doing baseball player things. He became an avatar for the seismic shifts taking place around the game, picked up and amplified by the vanguard saberists who were beginning to turn the sport upside down.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the important things to understand about the early Moneyball era — in fact, to understand about any sort of analysis — is that only so many problems can be solved at a time, and analysts tend to focus on low-hanging fruit first. This is also true of data collection. In the initial surge towards the glistening data veins, complicated events, such as, say, defensive plays, go unrecorded. The raw facts of hits and walks and strikeouts and dingers do not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I never watched Dunn hit live, I only started watching in 2014. While the classic left-handed swing is surgical, a la Ken Griffey Junior or Robinson Cano, Dunn’s was far more ‘lumberjack’, in the vein of Jims Edmonds or Thome. That opened him up for strikeouts, of course, but hey, watching a man spin himself into the batter’s box dirt was a novelty back then (rather than happening three times an inning), so that was kind of neat too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I’m not going to pretend that Dunn actually sparked off the three true outcome revolution that appears to have reached its horrific apotheosis in Rangers slugger Joey Gallo (63 percent TTO over a six-year career). But at 51 percent, Dunn was its first avatar, the icon of the new wave. It’s not his talent which made that happen, but the intersection of that talent and the sport-wide context it operated within.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But while baseball’s offensive game has followed Dunn’s lead, the drunkard’s search has been less rewarding with his defense. Back in the 2000s, it was easy to write off defense as a marginal part of the game. We could measure hitting. We could sort of measure pitching. Defense, however, was a fudge. And how important could a fudge like that possibly be?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This line of thinking is how Adam Dunn spent so much time in left field despite playing the position like a drunk giraffe attempting the limbo. Everyone knew, of course, that Dunn playing anywhere except designated hitter (unavailable to the National League Reds) was a disaster, but they had no way of quantifying the disaster. Eventually analysts started paying more attention to defensive work, and by 2011 Dunn had been more or less banished from the outfield.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the plate, Dunn was the harbinger of baseball’s future. In the outfield, he represented a blind alley, a place where sabermetrics as a whole got extremely lost for several years before groping their way towards a clearer understanding. While it’s not impossible to spot a clanger like Dunn trundling over the diamond, teams now put far more emphasis on defense than they did while he was at his peak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It would be silly to say that Dunn’s role is causal in any of this. He just happened to be at the right time and the right place to be the poster child for baseball’s offensive metamorphosis while also a cautionary tale for what can go wrong with too-easy analytical thinking. His career manages to sustain two wildly divergent, yet interlinked narratives. For he is Adam Dunn, and he contains multitudes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Poor Tommy John: Ruining baseball&#39;s future</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/tommyjohn/</link>
       <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/tommyjohn/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;When Tommy John injured himself in 1974, he was out indefinetely. Nobody knew what was happening &amp;amp; no doctor was able to fix it. Tommy John (TJ) was not a high-performer but a stellar contributor across his 26 years in the league. The &amp;ldquo;Bionic Man&amp;rdquo; started a revolution in the sport of baseball, which heavily impacts it today: he heavily bruised his elbow &amp;amp; got it fixed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When mentioning Tommy John Surgery today, friends of the national pastime show a disgusted face &amp;amp; grumble somthing like &amp;ldquo;looking forward to see him next year!&amp;rdquo;. What requires the procedure in the first place is the rupture of your ligament in your elbow (similar to the knee), which is then replaced by something from somewhere else of your body. As you might not from any MCL/ACL injuries, it takes time to train them &amp;amp; it is the same for your elbow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem though? Football pitchers &amp;amp; skiers break their legs over the years and they are fine (they are not, different topic), right? Technically this also applies to baseball, although the rate of it happening is alarming. Tommy John would normally occur to pitchers only (the people throwing 160+ kph balls at you), as they overflex their elbows to execute their pitches (throws) with a maximum of velocity &amp;amp; break. Yet, currently the system breaks with the highest share of athletes needing Tommy John being 15 to 19 years old (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/765898&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Especially at this young age, having underdeveloped muscles &amp;amp; core, the pipeline for pitchers dries up faster than initially planned. This furthers thinns out the number of pitchers available throughout the minors &amp;amp; major league, which is becoming increasingly difficult. Pitch count is the main metric coaches consider when replacing starting pitchers &amp;amp; bullpen arms. Looking at the age of pitchers getting TJ surgery, a worrying trend can be seen:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/age.png&#34;    alt=&#34;Pitchers are getting TJ surgery younger then ever over the past 20 years&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;Pitchers are getting TJ surgery younger then ever over the past 20 years&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a recent uptick, the trend towards early TJ surgery was in decline, where the median age in 2000 was 24.2 years bottomed out at 21.98 in 2016 (9.17% drop). Recent years went back to original levels. Nevertheless, the constant rise in TJ surgeries is alarming, being close to triple of what it was 20 years ago (29 to 94). A key ingredient backing up this up is the general level when pitchers get their first TJ surgery, which goes from college as a majority up to the big leagues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent years were a success nevertheless, focusing more on pitch prevention (staying below 100 pitches) as well as less intensive pitches overall (hello sweeper!). Overall, it might be best to start pitching the knuckleball again.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
