
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>Categories on Topics for a lifetime</title>
   <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/categories/</link>
   <description>Recent content in Categories on Topics for a lifetime</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <language>en</language>
   <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2024 - Philipp Enzinger</copyright>
   
       <atom:link href="https://pcorvin.github.io/categories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>Defense Industry &amp; Strategy in Austria as example of major NATO procurement</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/austria/</link>
       <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/austria/</guid>
       <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is an exemplary overview of a local defence industry and shedding some light on what is currently within the arsenal of NATO armies.If you have any other example or comments, feel free to reach out!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am from Austria is not only the unofficial hymn of the central European country, but also what I tell people asking me where I am from.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A first touchpoint apart from Schnitzel &amp;amp; skiing is the compulsory military service still in place, which somewhat makes sense for neutral countries (Hi Switzerland!).As I had to fulfill it in 2014, little did I know about how the cogs &amp;amp; wheels are turning regarding procurement of military equipment.Back then, the tools at disposal were by no means modern and limited investment meant a bleak peak into the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This seems to be no different to other defense apparati in Europe, where legacy platforms are maintained and only ever since the recentconflicts in Ukraine &amp;amp; Israel, modern stacks are applied &amp;amp; tested. Modernizing these systems (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://helsing.ai&#34;&gt;Helsing&lt;/a&gt;) orstarting completely new platforms (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://anduril.com&#34;&gt;Anduril&lt;/a&gt;) are only starting to win specific contracts against existing primes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-taking-austria-to-compare-it-to-nato&#34;&gt;Why taking Austria to compare it to NATO?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Austria is not part of the NATO (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Austrian_State_Treaty&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more explanation) but nevertheless represents a great case study on how &amp;ldquo;Western&amp;rdquo; countriestry to modernize their fleet but still spend a majority on flagship &amp;amp; existing platforms, diving into somewhat newer paradigms of the 2000sand only slightly touching new platforms to shift to a more dynamic arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main point focuses on the different systems &amp;amp; tools leveraged in the past years, with some outlook on how they can be merged in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-old-guard-traditional-arms-procurement&#34;&gt;The old guard: traditional arms procurement&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking at the most prized assets in the defense sector, two names will be directly flagged: &lt;a href=&#34;https://eu.glock.com/en&#34;&gt;Glock&lt;/a&gt;&amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.steyr-arms.com/en/&#34;&gt;Steyr&lt;/a&gt;, both local firearms producers.The former notorious pistol leveraged by regular police forces as well as special forces of the US, Germany &amp;amp; France. The latter exports itsAUG, an assault rifle, is used across the world, although also in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/world/syria-rebels-bolstered-by-new-arms-but-divisions-remain-idUSBRE91P0PV/&#34;&gt;parts you might not want to see it&lt;/a&gt;.Apart from firearms, Steyr-Daimler-Puch, unrelated to the firearms department and within General Dynamics, focuses on their Pandur vehicle.This armoured personnel carrier (APC) is built for internal usage but got recently exported to Belgium, Slovenia, Ukraine &amp;amp; the US.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These exports represented around 75% of the procured defense products out of Austria in 2021. Nearly all buyers are NATO countries, apart fromspecific NATO allies (Saudi Arabia, Philippines, Thailand) and other countries such as Kuwait&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, this reflects the current majoritarian spending of procurement budget within the NATO. Legacy systems are still fuelled, althoughshifts happened over time given the allocation of research budget in the past &amp;amp; seeing automated/semi-autonomous systems being integratedwithin the field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-shift-uavs--reconnaissance&#34;&gt;The shift: UAVs &amp;amp; reconnaissance&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://schiebel.net&#34;&gt;Schiebel&lt;/a&gt; might not be known to everybody, given their niche product, but is one of the strongest defense companies in Austria.Their main selling point revolves around Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs), which instantiate on a selected mission (althoughthey additionally cover a mine detection program) . This can be any  flight to take pictures of a specified target at alocation or monitoring infrastructure in remote areas. In defense context, understanding what happens at places you cannot directly reach(think enemy territory on the other of a mountain) and need high granularity (satellites will not work) is invaluable and can be covered byUAVs. Additional payloads beyond high-resolution cameras can be mounted to provide insights in dark environments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Missile types cannot be flown by the Camcopter (the name of Schiebel&amp;rsquo;s product) and only a selected number of militaries have them at this stage.Specifically autonomous drones, which are marketed as a new primitive, remain sparse, with mostly the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Atomics_MQ-9_Reaper&#34;&gt;Predator/Reaper&lt;/a&gt;and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TAI_Aksungur&#34;&gt;TAI/Bayraktar family&lt;/a&gt; being the only major products being produced at this stage by NATO members.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might have heard of other NATO countries having drones on their own or developing these on their own (UK, France, EU), yet they remaindependent on their counterparts for allowing procurement of the existing UAV infrastructure, which remains fairly limited&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-newcomers-osint--data-infrastructure&#34;&gt;The newcomers: OSINT &amp;amp; data infrastructure&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blackshark.ai&#34;&gt;Blackshark.ai&lt;/a&gt; rose to fame through Microsoft Flight Simulator. Seems odd, but the pixel mesh in its newest iteration was notas mushy as in predecessors thanks to Blackshark. Their work focuses on satellite data to be augmented by machine learning to include &amp;amp;extract more detailed information in real-time. Their &lt;a href=&#34;https://blackshark.ai/bisim-and-blackshark-ai-join-forces/&#34;&gt;deal&lt;/a&gt; withBISim is the start of their defense branch and more specifically to target capabilities with beyond the currentcapabilities with their annotation &amp;amp; finding tool &lt;a href=&#34;https://blackshark.ai/orcahuntr/&#34;&gt;Orca Huntr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The use case for national defense is in Open Source Intelligence (short OSINT), especially extracting as much information for surveillanceand pot. targets on a regular basis. OSINT has very much grown in recent years, with more intelligence agencies investing largershares of their budgets. UAVs &amp;amp; their reconnaissance would be partly complementary, although the former focusing more on strikesrather than the information gathering. Knowing as much in advance as possible is necessary to not waste any additional resourceswithin a mission, namely your UAV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These software solutions represent the new way of combative strategy and level up the possibilities to develop &amp;amp; validate plans forconcrete missions to determine how to leverage the existing arsenal. A key player is Anduril with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anduril.com/command-and-control/&#34;&gt;Lattice&lt;/a&gt;enabling C2 (command &amp;amp; control) capabilities for orchestration &amp;amp; coordination of actions. The NATO &amp;amp; existing large industry titans startedtheir &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.act.nato.int/article/nato-centres-of-excellence-command-and-control-c2-coe/&#34;&gt;initiative&lt;/a&gt; on their own, yet remains to beseen how novel architecture and tooling will be implemented within the upcoming years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;piecing-the-new-procurement-strategy-together&#34;&gt;Piecing the new procurement strategy together&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on the three parts, you can observe the switch from one step of the OODA to another. OODA stands for Observe, Orient, Decide &amp;amp; Act, a militarymantra to reach a decision. Whilst focusing on the Act part for most of the time, with soldiers being responsible for the rest, previous iterationsin procurement cycles were mostly spend on Act (again) and Observe. Only recently were Orient &amp;amp; Decide taken into account with the rise of MLsolutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, NATO &amp;amp; its members try to focus more of their budget research initiatives, clustering around autonomous systems (covering OODA whilst keeping the human within Decide)and new information gathering systems within their next generation of infrastructure (mainly on Observe &amp;amp; Orient). The major share of capitalremains allocated to legacy systems, with only limited thought in published strategies on how connect existing tools within the newset of requirements and the future of military systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is directly reflected within the defence industry in Austria: Major existing players staying on top, limited innovation to integrateinto new systems revolving around different aspects on the battefield than theirs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/DE/TXT/PDF/?uri=CELEX:52023XG0216(01)&amp;amp;qid=1681985654900&amp;amp;from=De&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://armstransfers.sipri.org/ArmsTransfer/TransferData/transferResults?logic=on&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unmanned_combat_aerial_vehicle#Current&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>UZR vs. DRS: FIGHT!</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/defense/</link>
       <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/defense/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;I love defensive metrics over everything. They have something of a randomness factor to this statistical game of baseball. You might ask: Why random?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of confusion and misinformation out there, so I’d love the opportunity to set it straight. I’ll outline the metric I’m most familiar with (UZR) and then dive into the other one (DRS). This is a specific write-up to unpack the overall complexity in defensive metrics for position players, especially under the circumstance of the respective pitchers &amp;amp; the ball in play.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit:&lt;/em&gt; Thank you Bailey for covering &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yT0dWF4BTbk&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. I might nevertheless add context in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Poor Tommy John: Ruining baseball&#39;s future</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/tommyjohn/</link>
       <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/tommyjohn/</guid>
       <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gQujXQQGOVNaiuwSN680Hq-FDVsCwvN-3AazykOBON0/edit#gid=0&#34;&gt;Tommy John Surgery Data&lt;/a&gt;, which provided all data used in this article!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Tommy John injured himself in 1974, he was out indefinitely. Nobody knew what was happening &amp;amp; no doctor was able to fix it. Tommy John (TJ) was not a high-performer but a stellar contributor across his 26 years in the league. The &amp;ldquo;Bionic Man&amp;rdquo; started a revolution in the sport of baseball, which heavily impacts it today: he heavily bruised his elbow &amp;amp; got it fixed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When mentioning Tommy John Surgery today, friends of the national pastime show a disgusted face &amp;amp; grumble somthing like &amp;ldquo;looking forward to see him next year!&amp;rdquo;. What requires the procedure in the first place is the rupture of your ligament in your elbow (similar to the knee), which is then replaced by something from somewhere else of your body. As you might not from any MCL/ACL injuries, it takes time to train them &amp;amp; it is the same for your elbow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem though? Football pitchers &amp;amp; skiers break their legs over the years, and they are fine (they are not, different topic), right? Technically this also applies to baseball, although the rate of it happening is alarming. Tommy John would normally occur to pitchers only (the people throwing 160+ kph balls at you), as they overflex their elbows to execute their pitches (throws) with a maximum of velocity &amp;amp; break. Yet, currently the system breaks with the highest share of athletes needing Tommy John being 15 to 19 years old (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/765898&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Especially at this young age, having underdeveloped muscles &amp;amp; core, the pipeline for pitchers dries up faster than initially planned. This furthers thins out the number of pitchers available throughout the minors &amp;amp; major league, which is becoming increasingly difficult. Pitch count is the main metric coaches consider when replacing starting pitchers &amp;amp; bullpen arms. Looking at the age of pitchers getting TJ surgery, a worrying trend can be seen:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/age.png&#34;    alt=&#34;Pitchers are getting TJ surgery younger than ever over the past 20 years&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;Pitchers are getting TJ surgery younger than ever over the past 20 years&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a recent uptick, the trend towards early TJ surgery was in decline, where the median age in 2000 was 24.2 years bottomed out at 21.98 in 2016 (9.17% drop). Recent years went back to original levels. Nevertheless, the constant rise in TJ surgeries is alarming, being close to triple of what it was 20 years ago (29 to 94). A key ingredient backing up this up is the general level when pitchers get their first TJ surgery, which goes from college as a majority up to the big leagues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/levels.png&#34;    alt=&#34;An uptick in especially college pitchers is worrying, from 2010 onwards&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;An uptick in especially college pitchers is worrying, from 2010 onwards&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When putting this further into perspective of the two key major levels with TJ surgeries, we can clearly observe that reversal happening:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/coll_pro.png&#34;    alt=&#34;College pitchers got back to normal, MLB pitchers escalating&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;College pitchers got back to normal, MLB pitchers escalating&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Especially in the early 2024 season, MLB already reached the TJ levels of the past years, with the season just starting. Most of the changes on a college level can be traced back to athletics department setting a higher priority on preventing elbow injuries through easy pre-season programs &amp;amp; less wear in games.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When considering the minor league system, we can relate back to the COVID times &amp;amp; the disproportionate number of wear &amp;amp; tear players aftermaths, as the minor league season was drastically reduced early on:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/minors.png&#34;    alt=&#34;The COVID hiccup in 2020 with a rebound in 2021&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;The COVID hiccup in 2020 with a rebound in 2021&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minor league injuries are at lower levels, especially compared to the number of total players in the system: Considering the ±270 players in a minor league system per club &amp;amp; the 40-man roster in MLB, the likelyhood of a TJ injury for one of the ± 14 pitchers is 4.62x likelier (5.083% vs. 1.098%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But what can we do?&lt;/strong&gt; Nothing. Especially offspeed pitchers are prone to TJ &amp;amp; will stay, given the extreme horizontal &amp;amp; vertical movement of pitches. Recent years were a success nevertheless, focusing more on pitch prevention (staying below 100 pitches) as well as the introduction of less intense off-speed pitches overall (hello sweeper!). Overall, it might be best to start pitching the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qusYTWQFIF8&#34;&gt;knuckleball&lt;/a&gt; again. Story for another day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
