
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>Topics for a lifetime</title>
   <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/</link>
   <description>Recent content on Topics for a lifetime</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <language>en</language>
   <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2024 - Philipp Enzinger</copyright>
   <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
   
       <atom:link href="https://pcorvin.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>UZR vs. DRS: FIGHT!</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/defense/</link>
       <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/defense/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;I love defensive metrics over everything. They have something of a randomness factor to this statistical game of baseball. You might ask: Why random?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of confusion and misinformation out there, so I’d love the opportunity to set it straight. I’ll outline the metric I’m most familiar with (UZR) and then dive into the other one (DRS). This is a specific write-up to unpack the overall complexity in defensive metrics for position players, especially under the circumstance of the respective pitchers &amp;amp; the ball in play.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit:&lt;/em&gt; Thank you Bailey for covering &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yT0dWF4BTbk&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. I might nevertheless add context in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Poor Tommy John: Ruining baseball&#39;s future</title>
       <link>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/tommyjohn/</link>
       <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://pcorvin.github.io/posts/tommyjohn/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;When Tommy John injured himself in 1974, he was out indefinitely. Nobody knew what was happening &amp;amp; no doctor was able to fix it. Tommy John (TJ) was not a high-performer but a stellar contributor across his 26 years in the league. The &amp;ldquo;Bionic Man&amp;rdquo; started a revolution in the sport of baseball, which heavily impacts it today: he heavily bruised his elbow &amp;amp; got it fixed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When mentioning Tommy John Surgery today, friends of the national pastime show a disgusted face &amp;amp; grumble somthing like &amp;ldquo;looking forward to see him next year!&amp;rdquo;. What requires the procedure in the first place is the rupture of your ligament in your elbow (similar to the knee), which is then replaced by something from somewhere else of your body. As you might not from any MCL/ACL injuries, it takes time to train them &amp;amp; it is the same for your elbow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem though? Football pitchers &amp;amp; skiers break their legs over the years, and they are fine (they are not, different topic), right? Technically this also applies to baseball, although the rate of it happening is alarming. Tommy John would normally occur to pitchers only (the people throwing 160+ kph balls at you), as they overflex their elbows to execute their pitches (throws) with a maximum of velocity &amp;amp; break. Yet, currently the system breaks with the highest share of athletes needing Tommy John being 15 to 19 years old (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/765898&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Especially at this young age, having underdeveloped muscles &amp;amp; core, the pipeline for pitchers dries up faster than initially planned. This furthers thins out the number of pitchers available throughout the minors &amp;amp; major league, which is becoming increasingly difficult. Pitch count is the main metric coaches consider when replacing starting pitchers &amp;amp; bullpen arms. Looking at the age of pitchers getting TJ surgery, a worrying trend can be seen:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/age.png&#34;    alt=&#34;Pitchers are getting TJ surgery younger than ever over the past 20 years&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;Pitchers are getting TJ surgery younger than ever over the past 20 years&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a recent uptick, the trend towards early TJ surgery was in decline, where the median age in 2000 was 24.2 years bottomed out at 21.98 in 2016 (9.17% drop). Recent years went back to original levels. Nevertheless, the constant rise in TJ surgeries is alarming, being close to triple of what it was 20 years ago (29 to 94). A key ingredient backing up this up is the general level when pitchers get their first TJ surgery, which goes from college as a majority up to the big leagues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/levels.png&#34;    alt=&#34;An uptick in especially college pitchers is worrying, from 2010 onwards&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;An uptick in especially college pitchers is worrying, from 2010 onwards&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When putting this further into perspective of the two key major levels with TJ surgeries, we can clearly observe that reversal happening:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/coll_pro.png&#34;    alt=&#34;College pitchers got back to normal, MLB pitchers escalating&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;College pitchers got back to normal, MLB pitchers escalating&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Especially in the early 2024 season, MLB already reached the TJ levels of the past years, with the season just starting. Most of the changes on a college level can be traced back to athletics department setting a higher priority on preventing elbow injuries through easy pre-season programs &amp;amp; less wear in games.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When considering the minor league system, we can relate back to the COVID times &amp;amp; the disproportionate number of wear &amp;amp; tear players aftermaths, as the minor league season was drastically reduced early on:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;mid&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pcorvin.github.io/minors.png&#34;    alt=&#34;The COVID hiccup in 2020 with a rebound in 2021&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;      &lt;p&gt;The COVID hiccup in 2020 with a rebound in 2021&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minor league injuries are at lower levels, especially compared to the number of total players in the system: Considering the ±270 players in a minor league system per club &amp;amp; the 40-man roster in MLB, the likelyhood of a TJ injury for one of the ± 14 pitchers is 4.62x likelier (5.083% vs. 1.098%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent years were a success nevertheless, focusing more on pitch prevention (staying below 100 pitches) as well as less intensive pitches overall (hello sweeper!). Overall, it might be best to start pitching the knuckleball again.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
